All right, chapter 13, female genital system and gestational pathology.
So this is a very important chapter for a few reasons.
Number one, you're going to see a ton of the pathology that we discuss clinically.
Of course, this is our major emphasis on the female genital tract,
and many of these lesions are going to arise commonly.
And then the other thing I would say is that if you understand the female tract,
the male tract becomes much easier to understand.
And so by mastering this particular chapter, the subsequent chapter in male genital
will also become much more straightforward.
The way I organize this chapter is to take you from the walk along the tract,
from the most distal portion to the more proximal portion.
And so we're going to start with the vulva, and then we'll go to the vaginal canal,
and then eventually to the cervix, and then to the endometrium and myometrium, et cetera.
That's the way we're going to do this chapter.
So let's actually begin with the vulva.
And the vulva, you're well aware, represents the skin and the mucosa that's external to the hymen.
So the skin and the mucosa of the female genitalia that's external to the hymen, that's the vulva.
It includes things like the labia majora, labia minora, the vestibule, et cetera.
And important to note that it's lined by squamous epithelium,
and that'll come into play a little later in our discussions.
Now the very first lesion that we're going to discuss is called a Bartholin cyst.
And to be honest with you, the only thing that you really need in order to understand this lesion
is to go back to review a little bit of normal.
So what I'm going to draw for you here, this is the vestibule.
The vestibule is sort of the opening to the vaginal canal.
So this central space in this square that I've drawn would represent the vaginal canal.
And what you need to remember is that over here, you've sort of got this duct that comes in,
and another one down here at the lower portion of the vestibule.
And behind that, underneath that I should say, is a little gland called the Bartholin gland.
And the Bartholin gland secretes mucus-like fluid, which lubricates or lines this vestibule.
And basically, that's the normal.
So if you understand the normal, then understanding a Bartholin cyst,
which is the pathology that we're discussing, is really no rocket science.
The notion here is that if you obstruct this duct,
then what will happen is you'll get a cystic dilatation of the gland behind it.
And so this will enlarge, and you'll be able to see on examination,
when you're examining the patient, that there's actually an enlarged lesion here.
Usually it's unilateral.
And so that would be a Bartholin cyst.
Now you could ask a few questions.
Number one, why would this occur?
Well, what happens is you get inflammation.
Let's take this normal side here.
You get inflammation, and that leads to obstruction,
and then the material can't come out of this duct anymore,
and so you're going to get dilatation of that gland.
Now, of course, this is usually going to occur in a woman of reproductive age,
and the reason it occurs in a woman of reproductive age is because
often these are related to infection and sometimes sexually transmitted disease,
and so that's the population that you would most likely see such an etiology occurring in.
And so therefore, that's the classic patient that you would see this in.
And by the way, this is not an uncommon lesion to see clinically.
Now, the other thing that can occur is that these things can become further infected,
and you can actually develop an abscess here as well.
But anyway, that would be a superimposed complication.
And the idea here is that, remember the general pathology principle that I keep trying to nail home,
which is that any time you block a tube, it's not uncommon to get infection behind that block.
So that's basically the Bartholin cyst, and it's important to know clinically because you'll see it,
and it's certainly important to know for exams, and what they like to do is show you a picture
or tell you a description that there is a unilateral lesion in the lower vestibule adjacent
to the vaginal canal, for example, and then you know that you're dealing with a Bartholin cyst.
So let's read together what I've written for you in the book, and you can follow along there.
So Bartholin cyst, it's a cystic dilatation of the Bartholin gland.
I've already explained that.
Again, it arises due to inflammation and obstruction of the gland.
We've done that.
It usually occurs in women of reproductive age.
The presentation is a unilateral painful cystic lesion, and where would that be?
It would be exactly where the Bartholin duct is normally present,
which is at the lower vestibule adjacent to the vaginal canal.
So basically, if this were to show up on an examination, it's an anatomy-type question.
They're just asking you where is the Bartholin duct or gland normally located.
All right, so that's really the end of the Bartholin cyst.
Now, the next lesion we're going to go to is condyloma, and this is super high yield, of course,
because these are relatively common.
This is a warty neoplasm that will evolve our skin.
Often it can be very large.
And the most important point here is that it's most commonly due to HPV 6 or 11.
Now, here I'd like to take a step back and remind you of a few very simple principles of HPV.
I'm going to highlight these principles here in order to establish a very important framework
that we're going to carry with us through the rest of our discussion of the female genital tract,
in particular the lower genital tract.
So let me begin by reminding you that HPV can infect the lower genital tract.
Now, that's important because basically HPV is going to infect, for example, the vulva, the vaginal canal, and the cervix.
That's what I mean by the lower tract.
So when we talk about HPV infection, these are the three places where you classically see it.
You can see it, again, in the vulvar skin, or you can see it in the vaginal canal, or you can see it within the cervix.
These are the three places in the lower tract, which really that is the definition of the lower tract.
When there's an HPV infection, one of the key features is that there's going to be coilocytic change.
All right, so I'm just going to say coilo here.
Now, coilocytic change is a change that we see histologically, and the way by which we identify that is you look at the nucleus of the cell, and it looks crinkled.
It looks like a raisin.
And I'm going to show you a picture a little later, but I just want to sort of lay down some principles in your mind before we go forward.
So just, I would like you to know that, generally speaking, an HPV infection manifests itself histologically as coilocytic change.
Now, you're well aware of the fact that HPV can be subdivided into two types.
It can be divided into a low-risk subtype and a high-risk subtype.
Important to know for examination purposes and for clinics what defines what's high-risk and low-risk.
How do we make that determination?
Basically, the question I'm asking you is, how do you know whether something is high-risk or low-risk?
Is it an antigen, or is there something that we measure, et cetera?
And what you need to know is that it's based on DNA sequencing.
It's the DNA sequencing that allows us to determine or subclassify HPV as high-risk or low-risk.
And that helps to remind you that HPV is a DNA virus, and, of course, that's a very high-yield principle.
Now, basically, the low-risk subtypes, the key ones, are 6 and 11.
And the high-risk subtypes, the key ones, are 16, 18, 31, and 33.
And those are the ones to be most familiar with.
If you're limited on time and you're having trouble remembering this, the big ones are 16 and 18.
But I'd like you to know that there's multiple.
I'm just giving you the four most common here.
So the most common low-risks are 6 and 11.
The most common high-risk risks are 16 and 18.
Now, what I'd like to remind you of is that if a patient gets infected with a low-risk,
and, by the way, what does low-risk mean?
Low-risk means low-risk to develop subsequent carcinoma.
And high-risk means high-risk to develop subsequent carcinoma.
Go back to our neoplasia chapter, and there you'll recall that we discussed that HPV is a virus
that has the ability to induce carcinogenesis.
And so low-risk means low-risk of carcinogenesis, i.e., development of cancer.
High-risk means high-risk of carcinogenesis, i.e., development of cancer.
Now, the low-risk, what I'd like to remind you of is it can infect, again, the vulva,
the vaginal canal, or the cervix.
And the classic lesion that the low-risk is going to produce is the condyloma.
And, of course, the condyloma is a warty neoplasm of squamous epithelium.
All right?
And so that's the condyloma.
And it's going to be due to 6 or 11.
Now, again, if you get 6 or 11 in the vulva, it's a condyloma.
If it's 6 or 11 in the vaginal canal, it's going to be a condyloma.
6 or 11 in the cervix can form a condyloma.
And then the high-risk, the key problem with high-risk is that the patients,
when they get exposed to the virus, they'll get the infection.
And as they have the infection, it'll progress.
And the main problem will be that the patients will get dysplasia over time.
And that dysplasia can eventually become carcinoma.
All right?
So, for example, in the cervix, we call it CIN, the dysplasia.
In the vagina, we call it VAIN, vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia.
In the vulva, we call it vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia.
So these are the different types of dysplasia that can occur.
And the carcinoma that's going to form is usually going to be a squamous cell carcinoma,
but it doesn't necessarily have to be, as you'll see when we get to our discussion of cervix.
Now, by the way, all of this is not necessarily written at this point in your text,
but it is written at a later point.
And so if you follow me here, I will, again, highlight many of these principles later.
But I wanted to just lay down this general paradigm
because it'll make our discussions a lot easier as we move forward.
So now let's go back to the text, all right, and then read together.
So condyloma, what is it?
It's a warty neoplasma vulvar skin.
It is often large, most commonly due to HPV 6 or 11,
again, characterized by coelocytic change, and it rarely progresses to carcinoma.
Now, I'd like to remind you, it's a low risk.
Low risk means there still is a risk.
So it's not zero risk.
It's a low risk, but it rarely progresses to carcinoma.
This is a classic picture of the histology of a condyloma.
Basically, this would be sort of the baseline of the epithelium.
And so this is the warty outgrowth of the cells.
And if I were to show you a higher power of those cells,
you would clearly see that this nucleus looks like it's kind of got this raisinoid appearance.
Look at the, compare it to this,
where this nucleus clearly has a very round nuclear envelope.
And you look at this cell, and this cell's kind of got this raisin-looking nuclear envelope or nuclear shape.
And so that's the coelocytic change.
Very important to note that any time you get an HPV infection almost anywhere in the body,
whether it be low risk or high risk, you're going to see coelocytic change.
So that's my little summary of HPV and the lesions that it can cause.
And we're going to keep hitting on this as a recurrent theme.
But for now, we're going to skip away from this and go to lichen sclerosis.
So lichen sclerosis, what this is,
is this is a thinning of the epidermis and fibrosis of the underlying dermis.
Thinning of the epidermis and fibrosis of the underlying dermis.
It classically presents with leukoplakia.
Leuco means white, and plakia means plaque.
So the patients have a white patch on their skin in this region.
And the classic description, for purposes of examinations especially,
and even when you examine this clinically,
is that it's parchment-like, super thin.
The skin feels almost like paper.
So you've got this paper-thin vulvar skin,
and they call that parchment-like vulvar skin.
This is usually seen in postmenopausal women.
There's sort of atrophy that occurs of the epithelium.
And then over time, there's some fibrosis of the dermis,
and that results in what we call lichen sclerosis.
Now, one very important principle here,
and that is that this is benign.
However, it is associated with a slightly increased risk
of squamous cell carcinoma.
You could probably bury that away for a minute,
and I'll touch on it later as you'll see.
Now, the other lesion to be familiar with when we talk about lichen sclerosis
is sort of the opposite, and that's called lichen simplex chronicus.
And this is, instead of thinning of the skin,
you actually get thickening of the skin.
So that the patients have leukoplakia, which is a white patch,
but it's actually, when you do an examination,
you actually notice that there's thick, leather-like vulvar skin.
And this is due to a hyperplasia of the squamous epithelium,
and the reason you get hyperplasia is because there's chronic irritation and scratching.
This is benign with no increased risk for squamous cell carcinoma.
So the way I think about this is sort of lichen sclerosis
represents thinning of the epidermis,
usually in a postmenopausal woman,
probably due to a little bit of atrophy
and then some immune damage that occurs to the dermis.
And lichen simplex chronicus, on the other hand,
is hyperplasia due to chronic irritation with scratching
and that results in a thick, leather vulvar skin.
So that's the lichen lesions,
or the lichen sclerosis and the lichen simplex chronicus.
Now the next discussion we come to is vulvar carcinoma.
Now here's the idea here.
A cancer can arise within the vulva,
and that is usually going to be from the squamous epithelium
that lines the vulva.
So you're going to get a squamous carcinoma, basically.
This is relatively rare,
and it accounts for only a very small percentage of female genital cancers.
It's going to present as leukoplakia,
and that's important because when it presents as leukoplakia,
you now have to distinguish it, right?
Because if you've got leukoplakia,
then the question is,
aha, is this lichen sclerosis?
Is this lichen simplex chronicus?
Or is this vulvar carcinoma, for example?
So a biopsy will be performed.
And when the biopsy is performed,
that allows us to make that distinction.
What's the most high yield in this discussion of vulvar carcinoma
is to know that there are two pathways by which vulvar carcinoma can form.
There's the HPV-related pathway.
So in this particular case, what happens is the patient gets what type of HPV?
High-risk HPV.
And what are the high-risk HPV?
16, 18, classically, or 31, 33, and then there are some others.
But 16, 18 are the real major players here.
So the patient gets high-risk HPV.
That eventually results in something called vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia,
or VIN, which is sort of dysplasia.
And then that dysplasia eventually becomes vulvar carcinoma.
So that's pathway A, and that's HPV-related.
Now the second pathway is called non-HPV-related.
And in non-HPV-related, the key sort of etiology or underlying cause
is long-standing lichen sclerosis.
Now remember, in lichen sclerosis, we have thinning of the epidermis
with sclerosis of the dermis.
And I told you that it's benign, but that there was a slightly increased risk
of squamous cell carcinoma.
And the reason I made that point there was because I knew
we were going to have this discussion here.
And so when you think about the non-HPV-related causes of vulvar carcinoma,
you really want to think about long-standing lichen sclerosis.
Of course, that's going to be important because, for example,
if it's HPV-related, you'd expect to see it in a woman of 40 to 50 years of age.
You know, she gets the HPV infection at around reproductive age, let's say 20, 25,
and then it takes about 10 to 15 years to develop the dysplasia.
So this would be seen, for example, in a woman of age 40 to 50.
Whereas the non-HPV-related, you know, that's a post-menopausal woman, much older,
and so you're expecting to see that, for example, in a greater than 70-year-old female.
All right, so again, what's the summary?
It's that vulvar carcinoma has two pathways.
Pathway A, HPV-related, which results in dysplasia,
and then subsequently results in cancer.
And then there's the non-HPV-related, which arises from lichen sclerosis.
So let's walk through this in your text.
So what do I say here?
I say that in the HPV-related vulvar carcinoma, it's due to high-risk types, for example, 16 and 18,
and it arises from vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia, which is really a dysplasia, also called VIN.
Sort of like, just like you would call it in the cervix CIN, here we call it VIN.
Now, there's also a non-HPV-related vulvar carcinoma.
This arises from long-standing lichen sclerosis.
And basically, the patients have chronic inflammation and irritation from that lichen sclerosis,
which eventually leads to the carcinoma.
And again, this is usually going to be seen in the elderly women greater than the age of 70.
So that's our discussion of vulvar carcinoma.
Now, the next very high-yield topic that we want to discuss is extramammary Paget's disease.
And this is really the final vulvar lesion that we're going to talk about.
Now, I've highlighted these principles in your book, but I want to explain it before we go any further.
So Paget, as I like to say, for the students who have seen me speak about this,
Paget was a very busy man.
He discovered many things.
You know, you've got Paget's disease of the nipple, you have extramammary Paget's disease of the vulva,
you've got Paget's disease of the bone, etc.
Now, in extramammary Paget's disease, and whether you talk about extramammary or mammary,
why don't we just say when you have Paget's disease of this skin,
for example, whether it be of the nipple or of the vulva,
the key problem is that you've got this malignant epithelial cells that are present in the epidermis.
So that's really the defining feature of the disease.
You've got the epidermal skin, and then you've got these foreign cells within there that are malignant,
that are sort of walking their way or present within the skin itself.
And that's Paget's disease.
Now, you can see that in the nipple, and that would be called Paget's disease of the nipple.
And you can see that in the skin of the vulva, and that's called Paget's disease of the vulva.
When it presents, whether it be in the nipple or in the vulva,
it presents as an erythematous, itchy, ulcerated skin.
And again, it's going to be due to the fact that there are malignant epithelial cells within the epidermis of the skin.
Here's what it looks like if we were to just look at it on histology.
This is clearly skin.
Here we have epidermis, everything above this basement membrane.
All of that represents epidermis.
And you can see that there's these extra cells present within here that don't belong.
And so this represents a malignant population of cells,
and these malignant cells are going to be indicative of Paget's disease.
And in this case, because it's the vulva, we call it extramammary Paget's disease.
Now, what's very important, and I would say the highest yield point about this disease and this location,
is that when you have extramammary Paget's disease, the differential diagnosis is carcinoma versus melanoma.
Now, why would we think about melanoma here?
Well, remember that in melanoma, we're going to have a malignant population of cells
that would also be present within the epidermis and could also invade down into the dermis,
but begins as a malignant population of cells within the epidermis.
And melanoma can also not uncommonly occur in the vulva.
One of the locations of melanoma is the vulva.
So we have to make the distinction here and ask a very simple question.
Is this carcinoma, i.e., is it extramammary Paget's disease, or is it melanoma?
And the way by which we can make that distinction is by doing stains.
And so the examiners love to play with these stains.
And by the way, we do this clinically all the time as well.
If I had a case come across my microscope, I would have to do stains to ensure what I'm dealing with.
Now, of course, Paget's disease, extramammary Paget's disease, is a carcinoma.
So it would be keratin-positive.
Go back to our discussion in the neoplasia lecture and recall that keratin is an intermediate filament
that would be present in epithelial cells.
It's the intermediate filament present in epithelial cells.
Therefore, if keratin is present within the cell, it must be epithelial.
And if it's epithelial and malignant, then we call that carcinoma.
So it's very important to note that we wouldn't see keratin in melanoma.
We wouldn't see keratin in lymphoma.
We wouldn't see keratin in sarcoma, classically speaking.
And so if we've got keratin-positivity, that indicates that we have a carcinoma,
and that's classic for Paget's disease.
Now, another important thing to note is that the cells would be S100-negative.
Why is that important?
Because melanoma is classically S100-positive.
So the defining stain here for melanoma would be S100.
Of course, melanoma would be keratin-negative,
and, of course, Paget's disease would be S100-negative.
Now, the last stain you'd have to be familiar with is something called PAS.
PAS is a stain that has the ability to mark mucus.
And if a cell is producing mucus, then it must be carcinoma.
It must be epithelial, because only epithelial cells make mucus.
So if it was PAS-positive, then we would call it Paget's disease.
And if it was PAS-negative, it would be a hint that we're dealing with melanoma.
But to be honest with you, this is really the way examiners like to go after this,
and this is really the way that we also clinically make this distinction.
We do a keratin and an S100.
Keratin-positive, Paget's disease, it's carcinoma.
S100-positive, melanoma, highly suggestive of melanoma.
So this is a very important point.
Now, I'd like to make one last point, and then we'll be done.
And that is we've got to make the distinction.
I've sort of used Paget's disease as a general term when thinking about the nipple and the vulva.
But I'd like to make one very important distinction.
And that is when a patient has Paget's disease of the nipple,
it means that there is a cancer someplace in the breast.
There will usually, almost always, be a cancer someplace in the breast.
But when a patient has Paget's disease of the vulva, there usually is no underlying cancer.
And that is a very important high-yield distinction to be made.
So the malignant cells are just within the epidermis,
and there is usually nothing underneath the epidermis in the deeper tissues.
And so, again, that's one very high-yield point to be made.
That is the end of our discussion of vulva.
So we'll stop there, and then we'll move on to the vaginal canal in the next section.